John Lehmann: An Inventory of his Collection
University of Houston Libraries
John Lehmann Collection
undated
Lehmann, John, 1907-
2 boxes
1984-002
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
John Lehmann was a poet, autobiographer, and one of the foremost literary editors of the twentieth century. This collection contains signed manuscripts, typescripts and galley proofs for two books: Poets of the First World War and Three Literary Friendships: Byron and Shelley, Rimbaud and Verlaine, Robert Frost and Edward Thomas. Also included in the collection are book reviews written for the London Sunday Telegraph, an essay for the Dictionary of National Biography, and a draft of a birthday poem for Roy Fuller.
Biographical Note
(Rudolph) John Frederick Lehmann, was born on June 2, 1907 at Bourne End, Buckinghamshire, England. Lehmann was educated at Eton, and studied history and modern languages at Trinity College, Cambridge. There his close friendship with Julian Bell, nephew of Virginia Woolf, plunged him into the Bloomsbury circle. By 1931 he was working at the Hogarth Press, owned by Woolf and her husband, Leonard. Hogarth Press published his first volume of poems, A Garden Revisited (1931). He briefly left publishing and lived for a time in Austria and the U.S.S.R. as a poet and a journalist prior to the start of World War Two.
His first periodical, New Writing, appeared in 1935 and by 1940 the series reached a broad audience both in Britain and on the frontlines of World War Two. Formatted to fit into the side pockets of combat trousers, it averaged monthly sales of up to 75,000.
Lehmann returned to Hogarth Press in 1938 as a partner and general manager and worked as editor of several anthologies showcasing the works of promising new writers. In 1946 Lehmann established his own publishing company, John Lehmann Limited. After the demise of Lehmann Ltd., he founded and edited London Magazine. He relinquished control over the periodical in 1961 and subsequently wrote several biographies, including Rupert Brooke: His Life and His Legend and Thrown to the Woolfs: Leonard and Virginia Woolf and the Hogarth Press, and three autobiographies which were collected, revised, and condensed into the book In My Own Time: Memoirs of a Literary Life. Lehmann also wrote several volumes of poetry, including A Garden Revisited and Other Poems and Collected Poems, 1930-1963, and the novels Evil Was Abroad and In a Purely Pagan Sense.
He frequently lectured in the US in the late 1960s and early 1970s. After a long illness and unsuccessful hip operations severely limited his mobility, John Lehmann died on April 7, 1987. The New York Times Book Review, called Lehmann "the greatest British literary editor of his time.... There is scarcely a writer [of his generation] in Britain... who hasn't at one time or other been grateful for his passionate scrutiny."
Sources:
Gale Literary Databases,"(Rudolph) John (Frederick) Lehmann," (accessed August 31, 2006).
David Hughes. "Lehmann, (Rudolph) John Frederick (1907-1987)," rev., Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, 2004.
Petra Rau, University of Portsmouth. "John Lehmann." The Literary Encyclopedia. 21 Mar. 2002. The Literary Dictionary Company.
Scope and Contents
This brief record describes a collection that is not fully processed. No further descriptive information is available at this time. Please contact Special Collections for assistance with this collection.
Princeton University's Rare Books and Special Collections holds another collection of Lehmann Family Papers:
http://libweb.princeton.edu/libraries/firestone/rbsc/aids/lehmann.html
Index Terms
Terms are either Library of Congress Subject Headings or taken from local sources.
Subjects (Persons)
Lehmann, John, 1907-
Subjects (Organizations)
Sunday telegraph (London, England)
Subjects
Poets, English--20th century.; Poets, English--20th century--Biography.
Formats
Manuscripts; Typescripts; Galley proofs
Acquisition
This collection was purchased from Burtram Rota, Booksellers, July 1984.
Open for research.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- English Poets of the First World War
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Carbon Typescript (Box 1, Folder 4-8)
  - Wagstaff Sue. Typewritten Letter Signed (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photocopied Typescript with Editor's Note (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
  - Photocopied Typescript (Final Version) (Box 1, Folder 14-17)
  - Author's Page Proofs, Corrected (Box 1, Folder 18-24)
  - Photocopied Typescript (Captions to Line Drawings) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Photocopied Typescript (Revised Captions and Photocopies of Illustrations) (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Three Literary Friendships
  - Autograph Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Autograph Manuscript Notes (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Typewritten Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 8-12)
  - Galley Proof, Corrected (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
- Book Reviews for the London Sunday Telegraph
  - Autograph Manuscript. "Siegfried Sassoon: Diaries 1915-18." [1981] (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Galley Proof, Corrected. "Siegfried Sassoon: Diaries 1915-18." March 13, [1981]. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "The Opium Eater: A Life of Thomas DeQuincey." August, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "Siegfried Sassoon: Diaries 1920-22." September 26, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Galley Proof, Corrected. "Voices From The Great War." October 11, [1981] (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "Voices From the Great War." October 30, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Galley Proof, Corrected. "Voices From the Great War." November 8, [1981] (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "Harold Nicholson: A Biography." November [1981]. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Galley Proof, Corrected. "Harold Nicholson: A Biography." [1981]. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed "As I Walked Down New Grub Street." December, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "The Gates of Memory." December, 1981. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "Vamp Till Ready." January 4, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "Roy Campbell: A Critical Biography." March 26, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Galley Proof, Corrected. "Roy Campbell: A Critical Biography." April 4 [1982] (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "The Diary of Virginia Woolf." Vol. IV. April 16 [1982] (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "I Was an English Poet. A Biography of Sir. William Watson." May 23 [1982]. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Galley Proof, Corrected. "Roy Campbell: A Critical Biography." June 6 [1982]. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Autograph Manuscripts Signed. "The Passage of Joy", "The Occasion of Poetry" June 21 [1982]. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Galley Proof, Corrected. "The Passage of Joy", "The Occasion of Poetry" July 4 [1982]. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "Bosh and Nonsense" September 16 [1982] (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Galley Proof, Corrected. "Bosh and Nonsense" September 26 [1982]. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "With Duncan Grant in Southern Turkey" September [1982]. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Galley Proof. "With Duncan Grant in Southern Turkey" September 19 [1982]. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "Blessings, Kicks, and Curses." November 2 [1982]. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "All Strachey's Are Cousins" February 15, 1983. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Galley Proof, Corrected. "All Strachey's Are Cousins" February 28, [1983]. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Autograph Manuscript. "Lydia Lopokova" [May, 1983]. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Typewritten Carbon. "Lydia Lopokova" May, 1983. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Galley Proof. "Lydia Lopokova" May 29, [1983] (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Autograph Manuscript Signed. "Cyril Connolly: Journal and Memoir." June, 1983. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Galley Proof, Corrected. "Cyril Connolly: Journal and Memoir." July 10 [1983] (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Essay for Dictionary of National Biography
  - Autograph Manuscript. "Henry Green." (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Draft of poem for Roy Fuller
  - Autograph Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 47)